Guide to the Toichi Domoto papers M1414
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Toichi Domoto papers
1860-1996
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Domoto, Toichi, 1902-
M1414
9.5 Linear Feet (7 manuscript boxes, 6 print boxes, 2 record containers, 1 map folder)
Japanese American Toichi Domoto (1902-2001) was a noted horticulturist who began in his family's Domoto Brothers Nursery and later founded his own nursery in Hayward, California.
Biographical / Historical
Toichi Domoto was the son of first generation immigrants from Japan who settled in California. Arriving in 1883, his father and uncle worked first as laborers and within a year were able to lease and then purchase a few acres of land in Oakland, founding the Domoto Brothers Nursery in 1884. They first specialized in the cut flower trade, and later, as pioneers in California's nursery business, they were responsible for the first plant importation of many important Japanese horticultural varieties of camellias, tree peonies, and chrysanthemums. They eventually specialized in trees, shrubs, climbing vines, roses, palms and ferns. Born in 1902 in Oakland, Toichi studied at Stanford University and the University of Illinois before joining his father's and uncle's business. He later bought 27 acres of land in Hayward and started his own nursery. His first catalog featured camellias and tree peonies, as well as magnolias, water iris, flowering quince and bonsai. He was interned with his family during World War II, but returned to his Hayward nursery and continued living there until his death in 2001.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains family and business correspondence, legal advice concerning the Alien Land Law of 1913, early nursery business records, early nursery catalogs (from the Yokohama nursery, the Domoto Bros. nursery, and Toichi Domoto's nursery), photographs of the Domoto family and early nursery business, class notes and subject files.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marilyn Domoto Webb and Douglass Domoto, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Horticulture -- California -- History; Japanese Americans -- California -- History -- 20th century; Domoto, Toichi, 1902-
- Geneology (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Re TV Show About Domoto Family (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Family Photos 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Family Photos 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence Toichi to Father 1923-25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- David Stan Jordan with Japanese American students, U of Illinois? (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence Mai Abegast, Nursery Related (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence Internment '42 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence DClarke - Nursery and Internment Related (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence Filoli, Nursery Related (Box 1, Folder 10)
- C. Strybing to Toichi Domoto (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence Personal 1917-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence Nursery Related 1909-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence in Japanese 1896-1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Anti Alien Land Law - legal interpretation 1913 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Recipes 1970s (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Nursery Photos, Historical (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photos Domoto Nursery 1988 Color (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Nursery Photos (23) (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Domoto Nursery Records - invoices, 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Domoto Nursery Records, 1902-1912 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Domoto Nursery Records, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Nursery Commercial Receipts (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Domoto class notes, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Class notes, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Toichi Domoto class notes, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Class notes, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Domoto class notes, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Toichi Domoto class notes, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Landscape design and cathedrals - Domoto (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Exhibit photos Domoto (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Eden Township History (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Domoto Bros catalogs and lists (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Tokyo Yengei Kaisha, Ltd. - catalog, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Kamo nurseries - lists (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Tokio Nurseries catalogue, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Yokohama Nursery catalogs, 1928-31 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Toichi Domoto Nursery catalogs (Box 2, Folder 15)
- CA Flower Market - History (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Plant photos (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Plant & Planting 1926 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Clippings, 1940-1941 (Horticultural) (Box 3, Folder 3)
- List of Plants and their color (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Tree Peonies - I (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Domoto's list and notes re tree peony and camellias (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Camellia list (w/ leaves) (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Photo - Camellia (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Iris Kaempferii; re Domoto calog (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Prop. Of grafting tree peonies - negs and prints, boxing trees (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Wisteria photos (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Notes (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Bamboos (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Bonsai - cultural recommendations (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Camellia cultivans (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Nursery (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Tree Peony (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Trident maple (brought from Japan by Domotos - at that time already 200 years) - now in Bonsai garden in Tacoma (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Japanese Quince - pamphlets nursery oriented (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Japan greenhouse industry (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Typescript (incomplete) (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Misc 2 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Clippings plant-oriented (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Tree Peony - Booklet (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Books - Nursery Oriented Japense (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Christian Texts (Books) (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Catalog - Photos Yokohama Nursery 1910-1911 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Catalog - Drawing - ? (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Catalog - Drawings - Chyrsanthamums (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Domoto Nursery orders, 1890-1899 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Strybing pamphlets - nursery (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Ledger records (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Notes (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Notes (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Publications (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous Publications (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Stationery (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Envelopes (Box 7)
- Misc Historical Photos (Non-Horticultural) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Certificates (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Scrapbooks (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Honors TD (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Honors Strybing TD (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Pacific Magazine, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Honors Camellia Soc. Toichi Domoto (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Hall of Fame award Domoto Bros (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Automatic Flashers by Toichi Domoto (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Strybing Society, F. Owen Pearce Award of Horticulture, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- California Horticultural Society 1962 Annual Award (Box 11)
- Catalog - Drawing lilies (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Catalog - Camillas (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Photo - plant (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Photos - flowers - color and b/w (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Photo - peonies in color (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Family photos (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Family photos (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Catalog drawings - Iris (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Catalog drawings - Peaches (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Catalog drawings - Orchids (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Catalog drawings - Peonies (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Catalog drawings - Water Lilies (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Catalog: photos of drawings of peonies, Yokahama Nursery (Box 13, Folder 8)